<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: maths | !geek]]></title>
  <link href="https://tech.endeepak.com/blog/categories/maths/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://tech.endeepak.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-09-22T09:46:52+05:30</updated>
  <id>https://tech.endeepak.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Deepak Narayana Rao]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Joy of finding a math series]]></title>
    <link href="https://tech.endeepak.com/blog/2017/10/28/joy-of-finding-a-math-series"/>
    <updated>2017-10-28T12:46:47+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://tech.endeepak.com/blog/2017/10/28/joy-of-finding-a-math-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was trying to come up with a question for preliminary logic round for interviewing. I decided to form a tricky math series and tried to figure out 2 math series which looks same in the beginning and diverges after a while. Something on the lines of</p>

<pre><code>series x =&gt; x1, x2, x3, x4, x5
series y =&gt; y1, y2, y3, y4, y5

where x1=y1, x2=y2, x3=y3 and x4!=y4, x5!=y5
</code></pre>

<p>So the question could be</p>

<pre><code>Write the missing number in below series
x1, x2, x3, ? , y5
</code></pre>

<!-- More -->


<p>To figure out these series, my approach was to start with some series x and find a pattern which doesn&rsquo;t hold good after few numbers. After few unsuccessful attempts, tried my luck with series of squares</p>

<pre><code>1, 4, 9, 16, 25, ...
</code></pre>

<p>Voilà! difference of consecutive squares were not only a odd number, they were consecutive odd numbers. Tried it for a long series and found it true for all the squares!</p>

<pre><code>1-0, 4-1, 9-4, 16-9, 25-16,... =&gt; 1, 3, 5, 7, 9,..
</code></pre>

<p>From what I knew of squares of numbers, this wasn&rsquo;t very obvious. I was very excited to check if this is already known or I was the first one to discover this :). Simple web search presented ton of articles on this observation.</p>

<p>That was disappointing but reading this <a href="http://mathcentral.uregina.ca/QQ/database/QQ.09.99/nghiem1.html">link</a> about a mathematician appreciating a student&rsquo;s effort in similar finding was comforting and encouraging to carry on with my quest</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
